Guide to the Robinson Family Papers 1822-1966 (Bulk 1860-1940) MS 520, MS 2309
@ 2011 New-York Historical Society
Robinson Family Papers
1822-1966 (Bulk 1860-1940)
MS 520, MS 2309
@ 2011 New-York Historical Society
7.0 Linear feet (17 boxes and 4 volumes)
The Robinson Family Papers document the immediate family of Dr. Beverley Robinson, his wife Anna Foster Robinson, their children Beverley R., Herman, Pauline, and Anna Robinson, and some extended family members. The collection includes correspondence, scrapbooks, dairies, photographs, and volumes related to the relations and travels of the Robinson family.
Robinson Family
Provenance
Donation by Estate of Pauline L. Robinson, 1968.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. (Researchers may not accrue unused copy amounts from previous days.) Researchers on site may print out unlimited copies from microfilm reader-printer machines at per-exposure rates. See guidelines in Reading Room for details.
Historical Note
1844 Beverley Robinson born in Philadelphia to Moncure Robinson and Charlotte Randall Taylor Robinson.
1845 Anna E. Foster born in New York City to Herman Ten Eyck Foster and Mary Pauline Lentilhon Foster.
1862 Beverley Robinson graduates from the University of Pennsylvania.
1863 Beverley Robinson enlists as a private in the State Militia and fights in the Gettsburg campaign. After his campaign is over, he moves to Paris.
1864 Beverley Robinson begins his study of medicine in Paris. He is later the first American to receive a French medical degree.
1872 Anna E. Foster helps establish the Monday Sewing Class, a group of women who sew clothes for charity. She becomes the group's first President.
1875 Dr. Beverley Robinson and Anna E. Foster are married.
1876 Beverley R. Robinson is born.
1878 Herman Foster Robinson is born.
1882 Pauline Lentilhon Robinson is born.
[18??] Anna Foster Robinson is born.
1898 Beverley R. and Herman Robinson graduate from Harvard University.
[1900] Herman Robinson receives his law degree and passes the bar. It is unclear where he studied law.
1901 Beverley R. Robinson receives his law degree from Columbia Law School.
June 1903 Herman Robinson dies of suicide at the age of 25 of a gun shot wound in the head. The body is found after his brother, Beverley R., receives a letter from Herman instructing him where to find it. His death is reported in The New York Times and on the front page of The New York Tribune and The Sun.
November 1903 Beverley R. Robinson is elected Alderman of the New York City 27th District on the Citizen's Union and Republican Party ticket.
1904-1906 Beverley R. Robinson serves on the Board of Alderman.
1907-1909 Beverley R. Robinson represents the New York City 27th District as Republican Assemblyman.
[1910-1921] Beverley R. Robinson marries Gladys Endicott. Anna F. Robinson marries Arthur W. Butler. Pauline Robinson never marries.
1921 Anna E. Foster Robinson dies.
[1922] Pauline Robinson becomes President of the Monday Sewing Class.
1924 Dr. Beverley Robinson dies.
Scope and Content Note
The Robinson Family Papers mainly document the immediate family of Dr. Beverley Robinson, his wife Anna Foster Robinson, and their children Beverley R., Herman, Pauline, and Anna Robinson. Although members of the extended family are represented, most of the correspondence, scrapbooks, dairies, photographs, and volumes in the collection relate to the work and travels of this immediate family. The collection is organized by family member, related family members, and charities. Unidentified items are grouped according to type of material. Some of the letters are in French.
The family member who is most represented in the collection is Pauline Robinson. The letters received by Pauline Robinson, daughter of Dr. Beverley Robinson and Anna Foster Robinson, as well as her scrapbooks and memorabilia, constitute a large amount of the collection. Her scrapbooks include documentation from society and charity functions such as invitations, pictures, programs, and lists of guests. Most of the other family members are represented in the collection only through their correspondence and memorabilia.
Other notable items include the elder Beverley Robinson's letters home while he was studying medicine in France and letters from Herman and Beverley R. to their mother Anna describing time spent with Teddy Roosevelt when President McKinley was assassinated. The collection also contains scrapbooks of letters to Beverley R. and the Robinson family expressing sympathy over the suicide of Herman. Almost all of the information on the suicide of Herman is located within these scrapbooks.
The collection supports research on upper class society, particularly women, in the late nineteenth and early twentieth century. Pauline Robinson's scrapbooks document the social life of a young debutante and the society parties, trips, and amusements she attended. The collection also has a significant amount of material on upper class women's charity work. The correspondence and scrapbooks explain the social problems addressed by the various forms of community work and the expectations of the programs. Some of the materials also document the attitudes of the women involved in the charities towards the immigrant or lower class beneficiaries of the charities, and the women's troubles dealing with bureaucratic city agencies. Since most of the letters are among immediate and extended family members, the collection also documents general family relationships. This is best shown in the letters to the family after the death of Herman.
The collection contains little material on Dr. Beverley Robinson's life as a doctor and Beverley R Robinson's work as an attorney. There is also no information on the elder Beverley Robinson's time on the Gettysburg campaign. Women, if married, are included under their last married surname.
Arrangement
The collection is organized by family member, family, or type of material.
The Robinson Family Papers have been organized into the following series:
Series I: Pauline Lentilhon Robinson (1885-1959)
Series II: Anna Foster Robinson (1852-1921)
Series III: Dr. Beverley Robinson (1862-1922)
Series IV: Beverley R. Robinson (1880-1926)
Series V: Herman Foster Robinson (1893-1903)
Series VI: Anna Robinson Butler (1896-1920)
Series VII: Extended Robinson Family Members (1881-1949)
Series VIII: Robinson Family Documents (1901-1921)
Series IX: Foster Family (1843-1908)
Series X: Lentilhon Family (1824-1897)
Series XI: Smith Family (1822-1903)
Series XII: Ten Eyck Family (1854)
Series XIII: Family Genealogies (1875-1896)
Series XIV: Charities (1872-1952)
Series XV: Visual Materials [1864-1966]
Series XVI: Printed Material (1868-1941)
Series XVII: Unidentified Writings (1863-1949)
Series XVIII: Clippings (1870-1956)
Related Material at The New-York Historical Society
Two school notebooks for Anna Robinson Butler, one entitled "Geography" and another one entitled "Current Events, 1905" can be found under Misc. Mss. Robinson, Anna.
Separated Material
There are four bound volumes in this collection that are kept separately from the papers. If an item is listed as a volume, please request it under BV Robinson Papers.
Foster family; Lentilhon family; Monday Sewing Class (New York, N.Y.); New York (N.Y.). Board of Aldermen; Parks and Playgrounds Association of the City of New York; Robinson family; Robinson, Anna Foster, 1845-1924; Robinson, Beverley Randolph, 1876-1951; Robinson, Beverley, 1844-1924; Robinson, Herman Foster, d. 1903; Robinson, Pauline (Pauline L.); Roosevelt, Theodore, 1858-1919; Smith family; Wharton, Edith, 1862-1937; Charities--New York (State)--New York; Circulars; Clippings; Condolence notes; Correspondence; Diaries; Europe--Description and travel; Invitations; Local elections--New York (State)--New York; Manhattan (New York, N.Y.)--Social life and customs--20th century; Menus; Photographic prints; Programs; Recreation centers--New York (State)--New York; School facilities--Extended use--New York (State)--New York; Scrapbooks; Sewing--Societies, etc.; Suicide; Upper class women--New York (State)--New York; Upper class--New York (State)--New York; Women in charitable work--New York (State)--New York; World War, 1914-1918--Personal narratives, French
- Series I: Pauline Lentilhon Robinson (1885-1959)
  Scope and Contents note
  This series includes the letters, scrapbooks, and memorabilia of Pauline Robinson, the unmarried middle daughter of Dr. Beverley Robinson and Anna Foster Robinson. The bulk of the series consists of Pauline Robinson's numerous scrapbooks which include clippings, letters and memorabilia regarding social events and charity work. The scrapbooks are in chronological order and two of them have been disbound and foldered for conservation purposes.
  The scrapbooks entitled "Year Books" specifically detail New York City social events. They consist of invitations and programs from dinners, concerts, plays, parties, dances, and weddings, and include newspaper clippings of the events and lists of those who attended. Pauline Robinson's volume "House Party Book," includes the photographs and names of companions who accompanied her on many East Coast trips. Although Pauline Robinson's own debut party is not covered in the scrapbooks, other social affairs such as Alice Roosevelt's debutante party and the Astors' Ball are documented.
  Also of interest in this series is a volume entitled a "Chap Record" in which Pauline has listed many of the numerous "chaps" who she is acquainted with, and has rated them according to various categories.
  Much of Pauline Robinson's correspondence is from family members describing recent trips or from others recognizing her for her charity work. Of particular interest is a 1915 letter from a Mildred Wallace describing her reaction to the sinking of the Lusitania and her personal reaction to seeing Jane Addams at a lecture on the "Woman Question." The writings in this series are mainly short essays or articles which Pauline Robinson attempted to have published. Other specific information on the charity work of Pauline Robinson can be found in Series 14: Charities.
  - Scrapbook, Clippings from New York Post, "A Collection Illustrating American Ideals and Characteristics", 1897-1898 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Composition Book, 1890-1891 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook, "Debutante Year Book", 1900 Jan. 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Scrapbook, "Second Year Book, No. I", 1900 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Scrapbook, "Second Year Book, No. II", 1901 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Scrapbook, "Third Year Book, No. I", 1901-1902 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook, "Third Year Book, No. II", 1902 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook, "Year Book", 1905-1906 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Scrapbook, "Year Book", 1906 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Cover of Disbound Scrapbook, 1902-1905 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Disbound Scrapbook of Clippings, Letters, and Memorabilia, Part 1, 1902-1905 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Disbound Scrapbook of Clippings, Letters, and Memorabilia, Part 2, 1902-1905 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Disbound Scrapbook of Clippings, Letters, and Memorabilia, Part 3, 1902-1905 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Disbound Scrapbook of Clippings, Letters, and Memorabilia, Part 4, 1902-1905 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Scrapbook of Social Activities, 1907-1908 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Cover of Scrapbook, 1905-1915 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Disbound Scrapbook of Clippings, Letters, and Memorabilia, Part 1, 1905-1915 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Disbound Scrapbook of Clippings, Letters, and Memorabilia, Part 2, 1905-1915 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Disbound Scrapbook of Clippings, Letters, and Memorabilia, Part 3, 1905-1915 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Disbound Scrapbook of Clippings, Letters, and Memorabilia, Part 4, 1905-1915 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Disbound Scrapbook of Clippings, Letters, and Memorabilia, Part 5, 1905-1915 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook, "Jerusalem and the Holy City", undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Pauline Lentilhon Robinson, letters received, 1885-1899 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Pauline Lentilhon Robinson, letters received, 1900-1909 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Pauline Lentilhon Robinson, letters received, 1910-1919 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Pauline Lentilhon Robinson, letters received, 1920-1929 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Pauline Lentilhon Robinson, letters received, 1930-1939 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Pauline Lentilhon Robinson, letters received, 1940-1949 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Pauline Lentilhon Robinson, letters received, 1950-1959 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Pauline Lentilhon Robinson, letters received, undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Pauline Lentilhon Robinson, Postcards sent to Miss Angelica Livingston from Italy, France, and Spain, 1952, undated (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Pauline Lentilhon Robinson, letters sent, undated (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Pauline Lentilhon Robinson, Writings and Speeches, 1895, 1917, undated (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Pauline Lentilhon Robinson Writings on Edith Wharton novel, The House of Mirth, 1905 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Gospel and Sermon Books, 1921-1922 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Pauline Lentilhon Robinson, Memorabilia, 1885-1941 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - "A Short Catechism for Young Children", undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Chap Record, 1899 (Box 16)
  - Recollections of Visits, 1902 (Box 16)
  - Pauline Robinson, Notebook of Writings, 1903 (Box 16)
  - Memorandum Book, undated (Box 16)
  - House Party Book, Photographs and Notes from Various House Parties, 1904-1910 (Volume 1)
- Series II: Anna Foster Robinson (1852-1921)
  Most of this series is correspondence. Anna Foster Robinson's letters before her marriage in 1875 are from friends and family and detail everyday routines and travel. A few of the letters are from Arthur Cummings, a former servant. Most of the later letters are from her children, particularly Pauline. Pauline mostly describes her domestic and overseas travels, many of which were at the DuPont estate at Winterthur. The correspondence also contains a few letters from the Robinson children that detail meetings with presidents or other famous people. Letters dated September 1901 from her sons Beverley and Herman describe spending time with Teddy Roosevelt on Mount Marcy. During this trip, Roosevelt received telegrams notifying him of McKinley's death and informing him of his new role as President of the United States. A 1899 letter from Pauline, shortly before her debut, describes a visit with President McKinley and the First Lady Ida McKinley. A 1920 letter from Pauline describes how her friend Edith Wharton looks "broken and subdued."
  Anna Foster Robinson's European travel diaries provide daily entries on the art, architecture, and scenery of the numerous cities and towns she visited throughout Europe. However, these accounts generally lack description of locals or discussion of current events in Europe.
  - Anna Foster Robinson, letters received, 1858-1865 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Anna Foster Robinson, letters received, 1866-1870 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Anna Foster Robinson, letters received, 1871-1875 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Anna Foster Robinson, letters received, 1876-1880 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Anna Foster Robinson, letters received, 1881-1885 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Anna Foster Robinson, letters received, 1886-1890 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Anna Foster Robinson, letters received, 1891-1892 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Anna Foster Robinson, letters received, 1893-1894 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Anna Foster Robinson, letters received, 1895-1896 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Anna Foster Robinson, letters received, 1897-1898 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Anna Foster Robinson, letters received, 1899-1900 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Anna Foster Robinson, letters received, 1901 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Anna Foster Robinson, letters received, 1902 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Anna Foster Robinson, letters received, 1903 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Anna Foster Robinson, letters received, 1904 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Anna Foster Robinson, letters received, 1905 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Anna Foster Robinson, letters received, 1908-1910 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Anna Foster Robinson, letters received, 1911-1921 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Anna Foster Robinson, letters received, undated [pre-1875] (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Anna Foster Robinson, letters received, undated [after 1875] (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Anna Foster Robinson, letters sent, undated (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Pencil Drawing by Anna Foster Robinson, 1863 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - European Travel Diary, 1869-1870 (Box 8)
  - European Travel Diary, 1870 (Box 8)
  - European Travel Diary, 1870-1871 (Box 8)
  - European Travel Diary, 1871 (Box 8)
  - Scrapbook of Religious Clippings and Prayers, 1852 (Box 16)
  - School Notebook of Essays and Vocabulary Words, 1856 (Box 16)
  - Address Book, 1872-1918 (Box 16)
- Series III: Dr. Beverley Robinson (1862-1922)
  The correspondence in this series includes letters specifically addressed to Dr. Beverley Robinson and letters addressed by the Robinson children to both him and Anna, (often Mamma and Pappa). The letters are mainly personal, from friends and family describing everyday events or travel. There is little correspondence regarding professional matters and some of the correspondence is in French. Almost all of the letters from 1903 express support for his son Beverley R. Robinson's candidacy for Alderman. The correspondence also includes letters from Beverley Robinson to family members while he was studying medicine in Paris during the American Civil War. Although Beverley mentions the cholera epidemic in Paris during that time, his letters mostly detail his homesickness and his studies.
  This series also contains writings and memorabilia for Beverley Robinson. It includes some of his published medical writings as well as certificate from Pennsylvania Adjutant General's Office stating he served for 90 days in the State Militia. Other than this certificate, there is no information on Beverley Robinson's efforts in the Gettysburg campaign in the American Civil War.
  - Dr. Beverley Robinson, letters received, 1882-1889 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Dr. Beverley Robinson, letters received, 1890-1894 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Dr. Beverley Robinson, letters received, 1895-1899 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Dr. Beverley Robinson, letters received, 1900-1909 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Dr. Beverley Robinson, letters received, 1910-1914 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Dr. Beverley Robinson, letters received, 1915 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Dr. Beverley Robinson, letters received, 1916-1923 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Dr. Beverley Robinson, letters received, undated (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Dr. Beverley Robinson, letters sent home from Paris, 1862-1865 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Dr. Beverley Robinson, Civil War Memorabilia, 1863, 1893 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Dr. Beverley Robinson, Medical Writings, 1875-1922 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Poems and Reflective Writings, 1894, 1901, undated (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Legal Papers to Stay in France, 1865 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Invitations and Receipts, 1895-1903 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Certificates, 1898, undated (Box 9, Folder 15)
- Series IV: Beverley R. Robinson (1880-1926)
  This series contains mostly correspondence and memorabilia belonging to Beverley R. Robinson. Letters that are addressed to both Beverley and Herman are included in this series. Most of the early correspondence are letters congratulating Beverley on his excellent grades in school. Later letters from 1903 are from friends and family pledging their support for his election for Alderman of the 27th Assembly District. Also included in this series is a scrapbook of sympathy telegrams and letters to Beverley R. on the death of Herman. The memorabilia for Beverley R. includes material on his schooling as well as a very small amount of material on his campaign for Alderman and Assemblyman.
  - Beverley R. Robinson, letters received, 1880-1889 (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Beverley R. Robinson, letters received, 1890-1899 (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Beverley R. Robinson, letters received (mostly letters re Election for Alderman), 1902-1904 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Beverley R. Robinson, letters received, 1915-1926 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Beverley R. Robinson, letters received, undated (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Beverley R. Robinson, Statement for Candidacy for Alderman of 29th District, [1903] (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Election Material, [1906-1908] (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Cutler School Honors, 1884-1894 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Harvard Entrance Exam, 1894 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - "A Short Catechism for Young Children", undated (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - List of "Knickerbocker Greys", 1888-1889 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Letters to Beverley R. Robinson on the death of his brother Herman, 1903 (Volume 2)
- Series V: Herman Foster Robinson (1893-1903)
  This series contains letters, writings, and memorabilia. The small amount of correspondence to Herman is from family members, and many of the letters are in French. This series also contains some of Herman's personal writings. Both his letter to the Evening Post entitled, "A Questions of Faith" and his diary from 1895-1898 contain thoughts on religion and philosophy.
  - Herman Foster Robinson, letters received, 1893-1903 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Herman Foster Robinson, Legal Writings, 1900-1903 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - "A Question of Faith" by Herman Foster Robinson, undated (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Cutler School Honors, 1886-1897 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Certificate of Admission as an Attorney and Counselor, 1900 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - "A Short Catechism for Young Children", undated (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Herman Foster Robinson, Death Notice, 1903 (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - Diary of Herman Foster Robinson, 1895-1898 (Box 16)
  - Appointment Book, "Herman's Last Diary", 1903 (Box 17)
  - Songbook, 1900 (Box 17)
- Series VI: Anna Robinson Butler (1896-1920)
  This small series includes two 1920 letters from Pauline describing post-war France as well as personal memorabilia.
  - Anna Robinson Butler, letters received, 1904, 1920, undated (Box 10, Folder 17)
  - Anna Robinson and Arthur Butler's Wedding Invitation, undated (Box 10, Folder 18)
  - School Report Card, 1896-1897 (Box 10, Folder 19)
  - "Snowdrops-A Selection of Scripture Texts", undated (Box 10, Folder 20)
- Series VII: Extended Robinson Family Members (1881-1949)
  This series contains letters, writings, and biographies of members of the extended Robinson family of Dr. Beverley and Anna and their children Beverley R., Herman, Pauline, and Anna. Each subseries contains only a small amount of material on each family member.
  - Subseries 1: Moncure Robinson, (1881-1949)
    These items relate to Moncure Robinson, Dr. Beverley Robinson's father, who was a famous civil engineer and a pioneer of the American railway system. His writings in this series include "A Survey and Report of Railway Transactions over the Allegheny Portage" and an obituary of his friend Henry Seybert.
    - Writings by Moncure Robinson, 1881, 1883 (Box 10, Folder 21)
    - Biographies of Moncure Robinson, 1889, 1949 (Box 10, Folder 22)
  - Subseries 2: Charlotte Randall Taylor Robinson, (undated)
    This letter to Charlotte Randall Taylor Robinson, Moncure Robinson's wife, is from a relative describing the good behavior of young Beverley, presumably the elder Beverley Robinson.
    - Charlotte Randall Taylor Robinson, letter received, undated (Box 10, Folder 23)
  - Subseries 3: Kenneth Robinson, (undated)
    This letter from Herman Foster Robinson describes his application for a position as Secretary in the United States Ligation at Peking.
    - Kenneth Robinson, letter received (from Herman Foster Robinson), undated (Box 10, Folder 24)
  - Subseries 4: Charlie Robinson, (1903)
    This subseries contains one letter from Pauline Lentilhon Robinson describing her social life and sightseeing in Rome.
    - Charlie Robinson, letters received (from Pauline Lentilhon Robinson), 1903 (Box 10, Folder 25)